<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An account of the growth of deism in England</title>
            <author>Stephens, William, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19943</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12290984</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12290984</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61457)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 195:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An account of the growth of deism in England</title>
                  <author>Stephens, William, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to W. Stephens. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Deism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58890:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58890:1"/>
            <p>AN ACCOUNT OF THE GROWTH OF DEISM IN ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58890:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58890:2"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF THE GROWTH OF DEISM.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TIS now three Years ſince you and I had a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Diſcourſe concerning the riſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of <hi>Deiſm:</hi> which is an Opinion of late Years crept into <hi>England,</hi> tho not ſo widely ſpread here as in other parts of <hi>Europe.</hi> I well remember we were both agreed, that there was no ſhadow of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why any one ſhould ſuſpect the <hi>Goſpels</hi> of Forgery, ſince the matter contain'd in them hath not the leaſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of any worldly Intereſt, or indirect Deſign, but all the Lines of them do only center in the higheſt Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Humane Nature is capable of. So that in conformity every Man may take great comfort in himſelf, and all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58890:3"/>Mankind live well with one another. Beſides, the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of this excellent Doctrine had at firſt all the Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements which an irreligious and idolatrous Age could give them, (as is confeſſed by their Enemies) inſomuch that nothing but their own perſonal full Conviction of the Truths they profeſſed could engage them to Preach 'em; and the intrinſick Goodneſs of the Law of <hi>Christ,</hi> was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to gain mens hearts, after <hi>Miracles</hi> had born down their Prejudices, and gain'd their ſerious Attention. In fine, you and I could ſee no reaſon to doubt of the Truth of any matter of Fact contain'd in the <hi>Goſpels,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the miraculous Birth, Life, Death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion of <hi>Jeſus Christ;</hi> but what would oblige us to deny the truth of all Hiſtory whatſoever. And from theſe Conſiderations laid together, we concluded that the Doctrine of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> was undoubtedly ſent to us by God.</p>
            <p>This ſtill made it appear more ſtrange to us both, how <hi>DEISM</hi> (which is a denial of all reveal'd Religion) ſhould creep in upon us where the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are made ſo publick, and where ſo many Learned Treaties are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, which ſo ſtrongly aſſert their Authority to be Divine. I confeſs, I was as deſirous to know upon what Grounds Men rejected the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as you your ſelf were, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I willingly undertook the Task you laid on me, <hi>viz.</hi> To collect and put together thoſe Motives whereby ſome had been induced to lay aſide all <hi>Revelation.</hi> For which Performance I was the fitter, becauſe it doth not require any Learning and ſtrength of Wit, but only Obſervation, and Inquiry, which I might eaſily make, becauſe of the numerous Acquaintance I have contracted in Town, where (you know) I ſpend the Winter, and in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where I beſtow my Summer Viſits. But all I ſhall do in this matter, is barely to give you a Relation of thoſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58890:3"/>Prejudices, and (as I think) falſe Reaſonings, which have drawn ſome of my Acquaintance from <hi>Revelation</hi> to <hi>DEISM.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Now, firſt I have obſerved, that ſome who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend themſelves <hi>Deists,</hi> are Men of looſe and ſenſual Lives; and I make no wonder that they diſlike the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Doctrine of Self-denial, and the ſevere threatnings againſt wilful Sinners. You may be ſure they will not alledge this Reaſon: But having read <hi>Spinoſa</hi> and <hi>Hobbes,</hi> and been taught to laugh at the ſtory of <hi>Baalam</hi>'s Aſs, and <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Locks; they proceed to ridicule the reality of all <hi>Miracle</hi> and <hi>Revelation.</hi> I have converſed with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of this Temper, but could never get any of 'em ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enough to debate the reality of <hi>Revelation:</hi> But a witty Jeſt and t'other Glaſs puts an end to all further Conſideration. Theſe are meer <hi>Sceptics,</hi> and practical <hi>Atheists,</hi> rather than real <hi>Deists.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. But there are others, who, although they have not a due regard to <hi>Revelation,</hi> are Men of Sobriety and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity, who with great freedom have let me into their Thoughts, whereby I can very clearly and fully (as I think at leaſt) diſcern the riſe and progreſs of this their Opinion, which is this;</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. In the time of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, (which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fineth my longeſt acquaintance with Men) 'twas uſual for Gentlemen to ſend their Sons abroad into <hi>Italy, Spain, France, Germany, &amp;c.</hi> to accompliſh themſelves by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. But leſt they ſhould be prevail'd upon to change their <hi>Religion,</hi> care was taken that their Tutor or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, who travelled with 'em, ſhould ſhew them the Idolatry and Superſtition of the <hi>Roman Religion;</hi> and alſo let 'em in to ſee that <hi>Popery</hi> in all its Branches was only a device of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> to carry on a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Intereſt of their own; to encreaſe their Wealth,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58890:4"/>Honours, and Power over the Lay-people; to exalt the Head of their Order above all the Crowned Heads in the World, and equal one whole Order of their Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, <hi>viz.</hi> the Cardinals, to the Princes of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> Nay, ſince all People were obliged to make their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions to, and receive their Abſolution from the <hi>Priest,</hi> the meaneſt of which Order could create a God for the People's Worſhip; 'tis plain, that their Religion was calculated for the Profit, Power and Honour of the whole Order of the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> in this World, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever advantages they might find by it in the other. Now the Young Gentleman being throughly convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of this Holy Cheat, returneth to Old <hi>England;</hi> where he meets with very zealous Conteſts about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (as was pretended) between the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> headed by Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> on the one part, and the <hi>Presbyterian Kirk</hi> on the other; and having carefully read the Debate (as it appeared in the Prints) on both ſides, with thoſe very Eyes which he had ſo lately cleared up in <hi>Italy</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> he could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to ſee that both theſe <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Parties, under the pretence of Religion, were only graſping at <hi>Power,</hi> and that the Controverſy at bottom, was not who's Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was beſt, but only what Sect of the <hi>Clergy</hi> ſhould make the beſt Market of the <hi>meer Lay-men.</hi> And as this Young Gentleman had before reſolved with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not to become a Property to the <hi>Popiſh Prieſthood,</hi> no longer now will he be ſuch to the <hi>Proteſtant Clergy</hi> of any Denomination, ſince both purſue the ſame Ends. He perceiveth that our <hi>Proteſtant High-Priests</hi> do all of them rival the Sovereign Power; the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s Houſe like that of the <hi>King,</hi> muſt be called his <hi>Palace,</hi> he muſt ſtill keep up his claim to the <hi>Miter</hi> and <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier,</hi> to vie with the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Scepter;</hi> and as the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58890:4"/>Stile of the King's Courts is <hi>Anno Regni noſtri,</hi> i. e. In the Year of our Reign: So that of the Biſhop's Court is <hi>Anno Conſecrationis noſtrae,</hi> i. e. In the Year of our Conſecration; the Year of the King's Reign being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known in the Biſhop's Court: The King ſpeaking to the People doth uſually call 'em his Loving Subjects; the <hi>Biſhop</hi> doth not make himſelf ſo familiar, but ſtileth the People of his <hi>Dioceſe</hi> barely his Subjects, <hi>Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioni noſtrae ſubditos:</hi> The King is <hi>Inthroned,</hi> and the Arch-Biſhop <hi>Inthronized;</hi> both derive their Power from a <hi>Divine Right;</hi> but the Biſhop is the higher Power, becauſe by the Principles of Epiſcopacy he can Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the King, <hi>i. e.</hi> forbid him the very Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of his Subjects, and thereby render them unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to make good their Oath of Allegiance, in yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Aid and Aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Nor do's he find that the <hi>Presbytery</hi> claims any infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Powers; each Party alledge <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> on their ſide; and for ought I can ſee, (ſays this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman) they are all in the right. Through an exceſs of Prejudice thus occaſion'd, he makes a further ſtep to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Deiſm,</hi> and Reaſons after this manner: 'Tis not impoſſible (continues he) that the ancient <hi>Clergy</hi> might be poſſeſs'd with the ſame Spirit of Pride, which has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd over the modern. If thoſe Writings, which they call <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> are of their ſide, as they all ſay they are, I make no doubt but they were of their own inventing; and if <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> their Patron, laid the Foundation of thoſe Powers, which both <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Clergy</hi> claim to themſelves from under him, I think the old <hi>Romans</hi> did him right in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with the death of a Slave. After this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I have heard it ſaid of late, by another of the ſame Conſtitution, that as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58890:5"/>modelled Faction againſt all other Chriſtians, ſo was the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by Law Eſtabliſhed, againſt all other Proteſtants, who were by Law excluded from every Office of Profit and Truſt; who were made ſubject to the Piques and Malice of every Church-man, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a conſtant Revenue to Apparitors and Spiritual Catch-poles. And though at preſent there be a <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> by Law granted, yet 'tis ſtill oppoſed by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Church, as appears by Sermons Preached at Viſitations, and the conſtant ordinary Diſcourſes of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> in which the Church of <hi>England</hi> is always repreſented, as at this time, in greater danger than ever it was; though I ſhould think the danger had been as great in King <hi>James</hi>'s Time: And notwithſtanding the Toleration (ſaid he) no Man can enjoy a place of Profit or Truſt, though he be ever ſo dutiful a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and ever ſo able or honeſt a Man, unleſs he hath a Conſcience by Law Eſtabliſhed: By which Church-device Men are deprived of the Privileges of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to which they are born, and for the diſcharge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they never did in any reſpect incapacitate themſelves; and hereby it comes to paſs, that the Nation cannot act vigorouſly in its own defence, being debarr'd the Uſe of one Moiety of it ſelf; and notwithſtanding this, they have the Confidence to tell us Lay-men, that we ought to love our Neighbours as our ſelves. Now if this be the way of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> (concluded he) let my Soul be with the <hi>Philoſophers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And this brings to my Thoughts what another <hi>Deist</hi> ſaid jeſtingly to me, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſince I was a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, 'twas lucky for me that I was of the Biſhop's Church; for though you were ever ſo Loyal (ſaid he) to the King, yet if you did not pay as dutiful an Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to the Biſhops, you could not hold the Place you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58890:5"/>now enjoy; for as certain as the <hi>Croſs</hi> is above the <hi>Crown,</hi> ſo ſure a thing is it, that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> will be above the <hi>King;</hi> which he undertook would appear to me if I looked back to King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Reſtoration, or King <hi>William</hi>'s Revolution. The <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> though they quarrelled with <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, yet became the loving Subjects of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second; joined with the <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palians</hi> in aſſiſting him to the Throne, and made no ſcruple of Swearing their Allegiance to him, and own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Supremacy. But after all this, the King was not able to ſupport theſe his Loving Subjects againſt the Power of the Biſhops, who in two Years time outed 'em of their Livelihoods, and after that, drove 'em five Miles diſtance from all Market-Towns; and at laſt the Acts made againſt <hi>Papists</hi> were extended to them. But ſince King <hi>William</hi>'s Revolution the Caſe is alter'd; for the <hi>Jacobite Clergy,</hi> though turn'd out of their Livings by Law, for refuſing Allegiance to the King, yet from the Allegiance they bare to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, they find ſuch Favour from their Lordſhips, that if the Livings they loſe are in the Biſhops gift, he ſhall preſent any Friend which the diſpoſſeſſed <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobite</hi> ſhall recommend; now what can be more by them deſired, than to enjoy the Profits of their Livings, and put in what Curate they pleaſe? And after all, that they may enjoy the full Profits of their Livings, and pay their Curates another way, theſe <hi>Jacobites</hi> may hold their Conventicles where they pleaſe, nay, Preach publickly and ſeditiouſly in an open Church near <hi>Cheap-ſide, London,</hi> without the leaſt offence to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Power. And is it not plain (ſaid this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) from all this, that on this ſide the Water as well as on the other, the Clergies Zeal for their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58890:6"/>Church and Religion, is only meant to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their own Party, Dominion and Empire?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Now the oldeſt <hi>Deists</hi> of my Acquaintance hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conceiv'd ſo great a Prejudice againſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, from the Behaviour of the Clergy, and having levened their Diſciples therewith, it has fal'n out unhappily, that the late Revolution has by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way alſo confirmed them in this their Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</p>
            <p>For the late happy Revolution, (which came on too ſoon, and was cut off too ſhort) though it was not ſo highly beneficial to us, as was by ſome expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, was yet of very great Importance. But as there is nothing in this World ever ſo good, but what hath ſome appending diſadvantage; ſo by meer Accident this Revolution, which has ſaved not only the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but (as I hope) the whole Proteſtant Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt throughout the World, has wonderfully encreaſed Mens Prejudices againſt the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and ſo by falſe Conſequence (ſuch as Men through Reſentment will make) againſt the Truth of Religion it ſelf. The old <hi>Deists</hi> tell thoſe of their Pupils, who never tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled abroad, that there is now no need of going over the Water to diſcover that the name <hi>Church</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth only a <hi>Self-intereſted Party,</hi> and that the <hi>Clergy</hi> have no Godlineſs but Gain. Have you not (ſay they) for many Years together heard them Preach up the <hi>Divine Right,</hi> and indefeizable Authority of Kings, together with <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> as the chief diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Doctrines whereby their Church approved it ſelf <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> beyond all other Churches? Nay, were not the Doctrines of <hi>Loyalty to the King,</hi> inſiſted upon more than <hi>Faith in Christ?</hi> and yet when their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Intereſt required it, their Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58890:6"/>was qualify'd by <hi>Non-Aſſiſtance,</hi> the whole Stream of Loyalty was turn'd from the King to the Church, the indefeizable Right was ſuperſeded by a miraculous Conqueſt without Blood, the Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to the <hi>Divinely Rightful King James</hi> has its force allay'd by another Oath of the ſame Importance made to the <hi>de facto</hi> King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and all this is Sanctify'd by the name of the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> their own Party and Intereſt, for the ſake where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is done. This is indeed keeping to the Text—<hi>Rem rem quocunque modo rem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the wretched Defence they make for this their Apoſtacy (ſay the <hi>Deists</hi>) maketh the matter worſe. For notwithſtanding King <hi>James</hi> is, as they will have it, Conquer'd; and his Throne, which was declared vacant, is legally filled by one who by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is declared our Rightful King; yet after all this Dr. <hi>S</hi>— will reſerve a Right to King <hi>James,</hi> though through Succeſs and Settlement he will allow a Right alſo to King <hi>William.</hi> And this Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Clergy generally adhere to, becauſe thereby they kill two or three Birds with one ſtone. <hi>1ſt.</hi> They preſerve to themſelves their ancient Right of giving Titles to Sovereignty. For though both King and Parliament have diſclaimed and damned the Conqueſt, yet the Clergy ſtill inſiſt upon it. <hi>2ly.</hi> They make fair Weather with King <hi>James,</hi> by keeping his Title alive, and by ſtill aſſerting his Right, open him a Door to recover his Poſſeſſion again. For what honeſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can oppoſe a Rightful King in regaining the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Throne, which is kept from him by a Succeſsful Uſurper? and <hi>3ly.</hi> They think they have obliged King <hi>William</hi> ſufficiently by the formality of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58890:7"/>an Oath, and owning him in his Poſſeſſion. Put all this together and 'twill prove, that
<q>
                  <l>When all the Argument is out,</l>
                  <l>'Tis Interest ſtill reſolves the doubt.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus (cry they) you plainly ſee, that your Church is nothing but a Party, to which whoſoever joineth himſelf ſhall find his Account thereby, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Error, Hereſy, Immorality or Diſloyalty to the preſent Government whatſoever; whilſt any other who is conformable to the <hi>Rubricks</hi> and <hi>Canons,</hi> whoſe Learning and Morals are an Honour to his Gown, and who is truly dutiful to his Majeſty, ſhall be excluded from all thoſe benefits his Profeſſion would entitle him to. Thus the bold Aſſerters of King <hi>James</hi>'s Right enjoy ſome of the beſt Preferments, and particularly Dr. <hi>S</hi>— ſits D— of St. <hi>P</hi>— whilſt honeſt Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> is ſtarving upon Charity.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> is a meer Party, (ſay they again) and has a Watch-word whereby they know one another, which they can vary upon occaſion. <hi>Non-Reſistance</hi> was the Word in King <hi>Charles</hi>'s days. For though at that time you did conform to every tittle and ceremony, injoin'd by Rubrick and Canon, yet if you failed in the Point of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> you were a <hi>Phanatick</hi> and <hi>Republican,</hi> a <hi>Rebel,</hi> and what not? Now if this Doctrine be contain'd in the Book of Homilies, as the <hi>Jacobites</hi> ſay, 'tis a Sacred Record of the Unjuſtice of ſome of thoſe who concurred in the late Revolution. The <hi>Shiboleth</hi> of the Church now is King <hi>William's de facto Title;</hi> And no Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to Homilies and Rubricks will make you owned by the preſent Church, if you ſhould acknowledge the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58890:7"/>King to be otherwiſe ſaid than a meer <hi>de facto.</hi> Now (ſay they) although we grant that Men will ſubmit to the Government, upon their own particular Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and therefore 'tis reaſonable that the King ſhould admit the Obedience of his Subjects upon what Grounds they pleaſe, yet we know no Reaſon why the Church ſhould ſet up the <hi>de facto,</hi> as the only Principle of Obedience: And when the King had better Titles to his Crown, as the Conſent of the People in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and his Matrimonial Title with the Queen, yet he muſt be made to pay the greateſt price for the weakeſt and worſt of all Titles; and give Dr. <hi>S</hi>— Sixteen Hundred Pounds a Year, for a <hi>Defactoſhip</hi> only.</p>
            <p>You ſee, Sir, that the <hi>Deists</hi> want not Occaſions for their Prejudices, how far ſoever they are from having Reaſon o' their ſide. And pray reſolve me, why muſt this falſe Title be ſet up as 'twere by the King's Conſent, to worm out the only true one? Why muſt none be preferr'd to Church-Dignities, but ſuch who come in upon this Title only? And thoſe who own the King's Right upon the Conſent of the People, be ſtill labouring under the Church's higheſt diſpleaſure? and poor <hi>Johnſon,</hi> a Man againſt whom no Immorality was ever objected, that is an Object even of the <hi>Deists</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, be left to ſtarve for the Cauſe? Nay, they have gone ſo far upon the Strength of Dr. <hi>S</hi>— Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation-Title, in Oppoſition to that of Parliament, that ſince the good Queen is dead, and the Conſent of the People, according to them, null and void; they have left the King a bare Poſſeſſion, without any Title at all.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I am acquainted with a Gentleman, who for ſome Years has not gone to Church, having taken offence at thoſe Practices I was now writing upon. This Man,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58890:8"/>you muſt know, had an extraordinary Veneration for the profound Learning (ſo he thinks much reading and common-placing to be) of a certain Eminent Divine, who had a fat Biſhoprick beſtow'd on him by King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> But he to requite their Kindneſs, when a Bill was brought before the Lords, declaring the King and Queen's rightful and lawful Title to the Crown, not only oppoſed and voted againſt it in the Houſe; but when it had paſſed, he entred his Proteſtation againſt it in the Journal. Nay (ſaid this Gentleman) if King <hi>William</hi> be only King <hi>de facto,</hi> then the Biſhop is <hi>de facto</hi> only. Truly Sir, you may believe me, that I was amaz'd at this Relation; for (as I then ſaid) though moſt Men look no further, than only to get Mony <hi>de facto,</hi> and do not with much ſtrictneſs inquire <hi>quo jure;</hi> yet 'twas ſtrange that any Man ſhould proteſt that he had no right to that Eſtate, which he openly continued in Poſſeſſion of. But I was ſoon anſwer'd by this his former Admirer, that if that Biſhop had ſtrengthened his own Title to the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick from King <hi>J.</hi> I might ceaſe my wonder.</p>
            <p>I am indeed ſorry to hear Stories of this Nature, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when they aſſure me of the Truth of 'em, and when I ſee the ill Conſequences of them. For though nothing be more certain than that the Baſeneſs and Falſhood of Man can never diſprove the Truth of God; yet when Men are highly Scandaliz'd, and greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by thoſe for whom they had Eſteem, and by whoſe Authority they in great meaſure governed themſelves, they will ſtretch their Concluſion beyond their Premiſſes, and diſown Religion in their Principle, becauſe 'tis diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded by ſome great Men in their Practice.</p>
            <p>But though to ſtrict Reaſons, ſuch Arguments for <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm</hi> appear ridiculous; yet from the Promotion of theſe <hi>de facto</hi> Men, I am told, hath ariſen great diſadvantage to the King, and thoſe Subjects, whoſe Principles and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58890:8"/>Practices have been always faithful to his Majeſties In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt: Since hereby it is, that it hath always been in the power of the open and profeſſed Enemies of the King to oppreſs his moſt dutiful Subjects. For theſe <hi>de facto</hi>-men, and the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> were but lately the ſame ſort of People, both of the ſame Principle and Temper. And though the <hi>Jacobites</hi> do now rail at them, for their baſe Complyances (as they term it) with the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>O</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution; yet the <hi>de factos</hi> are unwilling, for old Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance ſake, to paſs by their Railing, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand to ſhew 'em any kindneſs: And this they ſubmit to, as being Self-conſcious, that the <hi>Jacobites</hi> have a Right to reproach them; ſo that they are willing to appeaſe the anger of their old Friends by their beſt Services. Now the <hi>Jacobites</hi> having always an innate Hatred to the <hi>Whigs,</hi> (as they now ſtile all thoſe who think themſelves obliged to own the King for their rightful Sovereign) and being willing to keep up their old Maſter's Right to the Crown, (to which the <hi>Whigs</hi> are irreconcileable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies) eaſily prevail upon theſe <hi>de factos</hi> to oppreſs thoſe other ſort of Men, which is an Office they are as willing to undertake, as the <hi>Jacobites</hi> can be to put it upon 'em. Thus it cometh to paſs, that according as an open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Enemy to the Government ſhall dictate, a Church-man ſhall ſtrenuouſly exert that Power the King has given him, to diſcourage and oppreſs his Dutiful and Loyal Subjects. I will only (ſaid a certain Perſon) make a Suppoſition, to ſhew you how this may be; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King ſhould beſtow a Biſhoprick upon a <hi>de facto</hi> Doctor, and this Doctor ſhould there find his old Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance Dr. <hi>H.</hi> and being a Stranger in his Dioceſe, ſhould be willing to inſtruct himſelf in the Characters of Men from the good D., would it not fall out ſo, that the Clergy of that Dioceſe muſt be uſed well or ill, as the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58890:9"/>moſt open and notorious Enemy the Government hath, ſhall deſign? And was it not poſſible that the E. of <hi>N.</hi> might oblige his old Friends in the ſame manner? Thus, though King <hi>James</hi> be at laſt excluded, his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects reign in his ſtead. And whether an <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Abju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> laid upon the <hi>Jacobites</hi> Proxy-men, will put an end to this Corruption, Time muſt tell us.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But to return to the Reaſons, (or Prejudices I may rather call 'em) which occaſion <hi>Deiſm;</hi> It hath been obſerved to me, that where the Notion of a Church hath been carried on with the higheſt Tide, there even natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Religion is at the loweſt Ebb; as in <hi>Italy</hi> of old, and lately in <hi>France,</hi> where groſs Immoralities and Atheiſm are at the greateſt height. And though in our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we diſcarded ſome Idolatrous and Superſtitious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Practices, which were grown ſcandalous among the People, yet ſtill <hi>Christ</hi> was made to ſerve that turn, which his Holy Vicar can no longer do, <hi>viz.</hi> Support an Holy Order of Men in as haughty Inſolences, in as proud, ambitious and malicious Deſigns, as thoſe which King <hi>Henry</hi> (though a Son of the Church) and his Times could not bear. Now in anſwer to this, I bid theſe <hi>Deists</hi> only read the <hi>Bible,</hi> and ſee if the Spirit of that Book be not as good as their Thoughts can reach to; or let 'em read the Character of the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, given by Sir <hi>Matthew Hale</hi> in the firſt of his Three Letters concerning Religion, where he ſaith, <hi>It teacheth and tuters the Soul to a high Reverence and Veneration of Almighty God, a ſincere and upright Walking, as in the Preſence of the inviſible all-ſeeing God. It makes a Man truly love to Honour, to Obey him, and therefore careful to know what his Will is: It renders the Heart highly thankful to him, both as his Creator, Redeemer and Benefactor: It makes a Man entirely to depend upon, to ſeek to him for Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58890:9"/>and Direction, and Protection, to ſubmit to his Will with all Patience, and Reſignation of Soul: It gives the Law not only to his Words and Actions, but to his very Thoughts and Purpoſes: It bringeth a Man to ſuch a Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both of External and Internal Sobriety, as may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in the Preſence of God and his holy Angels: It cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and casts down all Pride and Haughtineſs, both in a Man's Heart and Carriage, and gives him an humble frame of Soul and Life, both in the ſight of God and Men: It regulates and governs the Paſſions of the Mind, and brings them into due moderation and frame: It gives a Man a right eſtimate of this preſent World; and ſets the Heart and Hopes above it, ſo that he never loves it more than it deſerves. It makes the Wealth and Glory of this World, high Places and great Preferments, but of a low and little value to him, ſo that he is neither covetous nor ambitious, nor over-ſollicitous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the advantages of it: It brings a Man to that frame, that Righteouſneſs, Juſtice, Honeſty and Fidelity, is as 'twere part of his Nature; he can ſooner dye than commit or purpoſe that which is unjust, diſhonest or unworthy a good Man: It makes him value the love of God and Peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience above all the Wealth and Honours in the World, and be very vigilant to keep it inviolably: Though he be under a due Apprehenſion of the Love of God, yet it keeps him humble and watchful, and free from all Preſumption; ſo that he dares not under a vain Confidence of the Indulgence of God, commit or purpoſe the leaſt injury to man: He performs all his Duties to God in Sincerity, Integrity and Conſtancy; and while he lives on Earth, his Converſation, his Hopes, his Treaſure, and the Flower of his Expectation is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and he entirely endeavours to walk ſuitably to ſuch a Hope. In Sum, it reſtores the Image of God unto the Soul in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58890:10"/>
            <p> I prevail'd upon one of my Friends, a <hi>Deiſt,</hi> to read thoſe three Letters, becauſe therein the Subſtance of the Chriſtian Religion is diſtinguiſh'd from the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials and Appendages; for want of which diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well underſtood, <hi>Deiſm</hi> has aroſe, as that great Man in the fore-cited Letter hath obſerved. <hi>When Men</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſee ſo much Religion placed by Profeſſors of Chriſtianity in theſe things which every intelligent Man values but as Forms, or Inventions, or Modes, or Artifices, and yet as great weight laid upon them, as great fervour and animoſity us'd for or againſt them, as almoſt for any Points of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion; They are apt preſently to cenſure and throw off all Religion, and reckon all of the ſame make.</hi> Thus that Upright Judge, whoſe three Letters my Friend having read, did well approve of 'em, acknowledging, that with great Exactneſs he had diſtinguiſhed between Religion and Prieſt-craft: And he added, If you will ſhew me, Sir, any Chriſtian Church where that diſtinction is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, I will become a Member of it. I recommended the Church of <hi>England;</hi> he preſently told me that he had read the 39 Articles, and obſerved that 3 of them were wholly deſign'd to uphold the Power of the Clergy over the People. And then he bad me only compare the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> which has been, and ſtill is, carrying on under the Name of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> with the Deſign of the Chriſtian Religion, as 'tis deſcribed by Sir <hi>Matthew Hale;</hi> and I ſhould find the one in all its parts a Contradiction to the other. 'Tis plain <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> the Clergy do not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of Sir <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Notions, nor will they ſuffer us to take any thing for Religion, that is diſtinguiſhed from their particular Intereſt. To what end have ſo many Perfecutions and Penal Laws been ſet a foot by the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy in Chriſtendom? was it to bring Men to any one Point of that full Deſcription of Chriſtian Religion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58890:10"/>which you cited from Sir <hi>Matthew Hale?</hi> or only to bring them to that ſhort Article of their Clergy Religion, <hi>i. e.</hi> to ſubmit to their Power? Did not the Honourable Sir <hi>R. H.</hi> lately write a Treatiſe, wherein with great Learning and accurate Judgment he diſtinguiſhed betwixt Religion and Prieſt-craft? and was he not treated for it with a true Prieſtly Inſolence and Malice in the Pulpit at <hi>White-hall,</hi> by <hi>A.</hi> one of their Majeſties Chaplains, and repreſented as a Scorner and an Atheiſt, becauſe he ſcorns to ſubmit to any Religion but what is of Chriſt's Inſtitution? Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Man ſhould govern himſelf by the Law of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and go no further, is there any Chriſtian Church which would own ſuch an one for a Member? If you will be a Son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> you muſt hold Kings and Biſhops to be <hi>jure divino,</hi> the Apoſtolical Doctrine of <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Obedience;</hi> you muſt not be indifferent to their Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, though declar'd but indifferent things; and the Reaſon is, becauſe you muſt have a profound Reſpect for the Power of the Biſhops, by which theſe Ceremonies were ordain'd: And beſides this, you muſt ſhew a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Abhorrence of all who do not ſubmit to the Spiritual Royalties of their Dioceſan Biſhops; for your Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip will not appear by any Mark ſo well, as by the Hatred you bear to all Diſſenters, in Conjunction with a deep averſion to all the ancient Rights and juſt Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of your Native Country. In fine, <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> when your Clergy Preach the Law of <hi>Chriſt</hi> without turning it to any By-end, or falſe Intereſt, you ſhall meet me at Church. You know the Clergy love Precedency of the Laity; Let them turn Chriſtians firſt, and I can follow.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I have known ſome, who have alledged as a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they have forſaken the Chriſtian Faith, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of Believing. Many Doctrines <hi>(ſay theſe)</hi> are made neceſſary to Salvation, which 'tis impoſſible to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58890:11"/>becauſe they are in their nature Abſurdities. I replied, That theſe things were <hi>Myſteries,</hi> and ſo above our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. But he asked me to what end could an unintelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Doctrine be revealed? not to inſtruct, but to puzzle and amuſe. What can be the effect of an unintelligible <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> upon our Minds, but only Amuſement? That which is only above Reaſon muſt be above a rational Belief, and muſt I be Saved by an irrational Belief? If a Propoſition be inconſiſtent with it ſelf, I cannot but believe it to be falſe: 'Twas once to ſerve a Turn againſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> your Church held all Doctrines neceſſary to ſave Souls, were plainly revealed in Scripture; How could you ſay plainly revealed unleſs you underſtood the Revelation? Beſides, I cannot think that the belief of any unprofitable Doctrines, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch as admit of no Application to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Duties, can be a ſaving Faith ſo much as in part; nor can I imagine that Faith tends to ſave a Soul, becauſe what we believe is only <hi>True,</hi> (for ſo the belief of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clids Elements</hi> might have a ſaving Effect upon Souls) but becauſe our Belief is <hi>Good,</hi> it has a practical Effect, and tends to make us better Men. Beſides, you all agree the Belief of your Trinity is abſolutely neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet widely differ in <hi>what</hi> we muſt believe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; whether three Minds or Modes, or Properties, or internal Relations, or Oeconomies, or Manifeſtations, or external Denominations; or elſe no more than a Holy Three, or Three Somewhats; or otherwiſe only one of theſe Three to be God in the higheſt Senſe, and each of the other two to be a God without Self-ſubſiſtence and Independence. I am confident, if I ſhould be perſwaded that an Explanation of the <hi>Trinity</hi> were neceſſary to ſave my Soul, and ſee the Learned ſo widely differing and hotly diſputing what it is I muſt believe concerning it, I ſhould certainly run mad through deſpair of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58890:11"/>out the Truth: But ſince theſe Doctors cannot agree which Party of 'em ſhall captivate my Belief in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his Faith, I will reſerve it to be the Hand-maid of Truth; whenever ſhe appears ſhe ſhall command it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I remember one Gentleman objected to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, that it made Men inſolent, quarrelſom and ill-natur'd. From whence I concluded, (as I told him) that he had never read over the <hi>Goſpels;</hi> truly he could not ſay that he had read 'em carefully, but yet that in reading the Hiſtory of what had paſſed in Chriſtendom, he obſerved that moſt of the Quarrels in which this part of the World had been engaged, aroſe from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions among the Chriſtian <hi>Prieſthood.</hi> Church-Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory is chiefly a Relation of Church-mens Wrangles, and D. <hi>Cave</hi> in a late Book of his had denominated every Century from ſome eminent Quarrel which aroſe among the Clergy. But beſides this, what was the Holy War, what all the holy Maſſacres and Croiſados which filled <hi>Europe</hi> with Blood, but the Inventions of Holy Church? And what is holy Inquiſition, but a perpetual Series of Murthers carry'd on in barbarous Forms of Law againſt the common Senſe of Mankind? Does Hiſtory account for any Barbarities ſo great as thoſe committed by the Popes? Any Cruelties ſo ſavage as thoſe of the Holy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition? Any Murthers ſo ſolemn, and religiouſly bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal as the Acts of Faith? Any Pragmaticalneſs ſo inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable as that of the Jeſuits? is not their Humanity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed by their Chriſtian Religion? ſuch is their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice that no Man can eat Bread where they have to do, unleſs he ſubmit his Faith to their guidance, witneſs the preſent <hi>French</hi> Perſecution. Nor can any Sovereign Prince keep his Word or Oath, though he had only ſworn to maintain thoſe Laws by which he Reigns as King, any longer than this Spiritual Fatherhood will give him leave,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58890:12"/>as <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>James.</hi> II. of <hi>England</hi> do witneſs. Let theſe Inhumanities be conſidered, as ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and carried on by the name of Catholick Church, and (if the Devils believe) you may as decently ſay Church of <hi>Hell</hi> as Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as Devotion, continu'd our <hi>Deist,</hi> to holy Church is the center upon which all things turn on the other ſide the Water, ſo is it the ſame thing here. Do not our Prieſthood of <hi>England</hi> make as high Pretences to diſpoſe of all Offices and Truſts in the Kingdom, to thoſe of their own Faction, as thoſe of <hi>Rome?</hi> Have they not long ſince got their Bill of Excluſion to be paſſed into a Law, whereby no Man can enjoy a Place of Profit or Truſt in the State, but whom they qualify at their Altars? where Men were capacitated to be Bumbails, keep Gaming-houſes and ſell Ale. What was it but the Inſolence of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that brought about Father <hi>Laud</hi>'s and Father <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Revolutions? Beſides (ſaid he) do you not obſerve what a keen Edge Chriſtian Faith puts upon the ill-nature of Divines, when they are diſputing about matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? 'Tis common for Philoſophers, Lawyers, Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to differ about matters which concern their Profeſſions, and write one againſt another: But you will find ſome Temper and Decorum obſerved in their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. But let the Controverſy be about any Branch of Chriſtian Faith; and then ſee the <hi>Odium Theologorum,</hi> the Malice of Divines in the late Writings of two of your Church Doctors againſt each other; at leaſt this ſhews that Chriſtian Faith doth not improve the Temper of ſuch Men who are of mean Birth, and narrow Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. And I cannot but obſerve, that your <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Malice is under a worſe Management than the <hi>Popiſh;</hi> they only thirſt for the Blood of Proteſtants, but you are for ſucking one anothers Blood; as when for the Service
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58890:12"/>of King <hi>Charles</hi> the II. (who was Head of your Church) and his Popiſh Brother, the Blood of the beſt Proteſtants in <hi>England,</hi> (and ſome of them of your own Church) was to be ſpilt, the Court Blood-ſuckers, <hi>viz.</hi> Attorney general, and Judges, beſides Juries and Evidence, were all of 'em choſen Men out of your own Church; and the <hi>Poſſe</hi> of the Clergy was raiſed to hold their Heads to the Block, by Preaching the Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in requital, it muſt be confeſſed, that your Clergy require the King to do their Perſecuting Journey-work with the ſame Inſolence as the Popiſh Prieſthood uſe; For muſt not the Sovereign Monarch of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by his Authority Royal, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Decrees and Anathema's of the Arch-deacons and Biſhops Chancellors, by Impriſoning his loyal and uſeful Subjects, for not conforming to their Ceremonies? If a King will ſubmit to this Drudgery, he ſhall have the <hi>vox Cleri</hi> of his ſide, and be as great as Noiſe and fulſom Flattery can make him; but in the mean time is really King but of one Moiety of his People, whilſt the danger which the other half apprehend from the Secular Arm directed by Spiritual Power of Neceſſity, weaneth their Hearts from the Government. Thus <hi>Charles</hi> the II. who for two Years after his Return, reigned in the Hearts of all his People, was by the Act of Uniformity reduced to be King of the Church-party; and at laſt, whilſt the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Prieſthood zealouſly contended whoſe Property he ſhould be, (like the Truth among Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſial Divines) he was loſt in the Scuffle.</p>
            <p>He inſtanced in likewiſe the late King <hi>James,</hi> who (ſaid he) had it in his power to be univerſally beloved and obey'd, beyond any King of <hi>England</hi> this Age has produced. His Right to the Crown was owned by all; his Wilfulneſs had paſſed upon the Church of <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:58890:13"/>Party for Magnanimous Reſolution, which ſtruck ſuch an Awe upon them, that they were coming to a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and would have conſented to a Toleration of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters, and <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks too, provided their Maintenance might be continued to them. Thus the Heart of all <hi>England</hi> had been ſet upon the King; but the Popiſh Prieſthood would be content with nothing leſs than delivering the whole Nation to Satan, and their King muſt execute the dreadful Anathema, though 'twas manifeſt that he muſt thereby leſſen himſelf to the ſize of one of the 7 Kings of <hi>Kent;</hi> for he could be Sovereign of no more than the Two hundredth part of the People. For King <hi>Charles</hi> in numbering the People, had found that the Proportion between <hi>Papist</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> was as 1 to 200: whereas had his own Prieſthood been ſo favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him, as to have excuſed him from executing that Satanical Power, which by a Right purely Divine was veſted in Sacred Majeſty, his Reign might have been happy, and his Memory precious. What an unhappy Effect had the Spirit of Father <hi>Laud</hi> upon King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt? And what hath brought <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. to the preſent Diminution of his Glory, but that haughty Inſolence and unnatural Cruelty in Perſecuting his own Subjects, which Father <hi>la Chaiſe</hi> has inſpired him with? What Figure will this Grand Monarch make in Story? His Name will pollute the Annals of this Age, and his cowardly Conqueſts be the Scorn of Poſterity. Now from all that he had ſaid, he concluded, that for Luck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, as well as to preſerve his good Nature, he would be cautious of being (at leaſt) a zealous Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="8">8. 'Twas not long ſince I met one of my old Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, who told me that he had lately caſt off theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices he had conceived againſt the Chriſtian Faith, by the Aſſiſtance of a Book called, <hi>The Five Letters of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:58890:13"/>By the laſt of thoſe Letters he was convinced of the reality of reveal'd Religion, from the Intrinſick va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and Excellency thereof; and he was fully confirmed in his Judgment by a late Book called, <hi>The Reaſonableneſs of Chriſtianity, as delivered in the Scripture.</hi> Upon this, he had read over the <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi> once, and the <hi>New</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, with great attention of Mind. Indeed he always thought the Moral part of the <hi>Bible</hi> very good; but then he alſo thought, that by the ſtrength of his own Reaſon, he could have written as good a Moral himſelf. But by the laſt of theſe Books he was convinced, that he was indebted to <hi>Revelation</hi> more than he thought of, and conſidering how long the Ceremonial Law had obtain'd among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and what a profound reſpect they paid to the Scribes, Phariſees, and Spiritual Guides and Rulers; he plainly ſaw that there was need enough of Miracle to bear down their Prejudices, to make 'em leave their Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and liſten to that excellent Moral which Chriſt gave 'em; nay, he was convinced that no Miracles were ſtrong enough to prevail over the Prieſt, or a Prieſt-ridden People, to become Proſelytes to the Doctrine of univerſal Love and Charity; for (ſaid he) if a Teacher ſhould now be ſent from Heaven with this Meſſage, that all the Proteſtant Parties in <hi>England</hi> ſhould be reconciled and live well with one another, making nothing neceſſary to their religious Communion, but what Chriſt had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſuch Circumſtances as Time and Place, and what in the nature of the thing was needful, and if this Teacher's Miſſion were confirm'd by Miracle, it would have (as he thought) no better effect upon our ſeveral Sects of Clergy, and thoſe who are bigotted to their Parties, than it had upon the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and their Diſciples of old.</p>
            <p>Having heard him ſpeak ſo ſharply againſt the Clergy after his old way, I could not but tell him that I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58890:14"/>he was but almoſt a Chriſtian; for he who loveth the Inſtitution of Chriſt, cannot but reſpect thoſe who are the Miniſters thereof; at leaſt, I hoped that he would pay a reſpect to the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which was the beſt Reformed Church in the World; and therefore I expected that he was already a Member of our Church: He reply'd, that he ſhould always be ready to pay his reſpect to every good Man of what Order or Degree ſoever; he ſhould always be willing to hear a good Miniſter Preach the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt to him, and exhort him to the ſincere Practice of it. That he was ready to contribute his ſhare to the Maintenance of ſuch Miniſters, and to join with that Church-of-<hi>England</hi> Congregation near to which he liv'd, in publick Worſhip; but yet he could not condemn the Worſhip of other Congregations, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude himſelf from joyning with them as occaſion ſhould ſerve him. So that as to Church-memberſhip he could be a Member of any Church, which would own him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the terms of Faith and Practice, contained in the Book he mentioned, concerning the Reaſonableneſs of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion,</hi> &amp;c. But ſtill he conceiv'd, that Church-Communion in holy Offices was deſigned only to raiſe his Devotion towards God, not towards the Clergy, which made him admire the unparallell'd Impudence of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Prieſthood, who meaſure the Religion of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by their Devotion to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> i. e. indeed to themſelves; and he doubted whether any Church were ſufficiently Reformed from Popery, which made any Doctrines of Faith neceſſary to Salvation that were not declared ſo in the Goſpels, and where the Clergy would always diſtinguiſh between Church and State, and give the Precedency to themſelves. But yet he would join with any Church as far as it promoted the Honour of God, and ſeparate from it, wherein on pretence of Religion, he ſaw, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at it aimed at a By-end of its own.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58890:14"/>
            <p> Here I urged him again to joyn to our Church, which had no other deſign but God's Glory. To this he ſaid, that he ſhould be glad that the Church of <hi>England</hi> would own him, though he could not be of their Party: He would willingly paſs as a Church-man for his Credit-ſake; for (ſaid he) though a Man doth ever ſo firmly believe Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to be the Meſſiah whom God had of old promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and in due time ſent to give us a perfect Rule of Life, in order to make us truly religious here, and ever happy hereafter; and though a Man ſhould ſhew forth his Faith by an agreeable courſe of Life, in doing Juſtice, loving Mercy, and an humble walking with God; yet if he were not owned as a Member of ſome Church, he would by all Churches be accounted, if not an Atheiſt, yet a Sceptic, a Man of no ſettled Principle, but own who has his Religion to chooſe. For if you look over the State of Religion as it ſtandeth in Chriſtendom, there is no Church whatſoever which will accept you as a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of its Communion, but upon ſome particular terms of Belief, or Practice, which Chriſt never appointed, and it may be ſuch as an honeſt and a wiſe Chriſtian cannot conſent to. I am not more able to give up my Reaſon to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than to give up my Senſes to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> it looks like a Trick in all Churches to take away the uſe of Mens Reaſon, that they may render us Vaſſals and Slaves to all their Dictates and Commands. But what greater ſlavery than to force on Men a Belief of ſuch things as neceſſary to Salvation, of which 'tis not poſſible to form any Idea? Though I am ſatisfied there is no ſuch thing as a change of Bread into the Fleſh of Chriſt, yet I can form an Idea, that ſuch a thing may be, that the ſame Power which changed Earth into a Man, may change Bread into Fleſh: But I can frame to my ſelf no Idea of what your Church Teacheth in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58890:15"/>that the Body and Blood of Chriſt are <hi>verily and indeed taken and received of the faithful;</hi> And when I ask how can this be underſtood by a Proteſtant, who believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that there is no other Body but that of Bread? I am told that the Church meaneth it in a Spiritual Senſe. Now I have try'd, and find it impoſſible for me to form to my ſelf an Idea of a Body verily and indeed in a Spiritual Senſe.</p>
            <p>And therefore I muſt ſay 'tis an unwiſe and a hard Thing for any Church to impoſe abſurd or unintelligible Notions (eſpecially ſuch Speculations, which tend to make no body the better) as neceſſary to Salvation; for Wiſe Men, and ſuch who will take Courage to examine what they Believe, will not ſubmit to ſuch an Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and weak Men are kept all their Life long in Fears and Doubts of their Eternal State, as being always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain whether they firmly believe ſuch Doctrines, or no.</p>
            <p>Beſides this (ſaid he) your Church will require me to believe other Abſurdities as bad as theſe, as that Kings and Biſhops have a Divine Right to that Power, which they exerciſe over us, whereas with my own Eyes I ſaw our Great and Gracious King accept the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as the Gift of the People. And I ſee as plainly, that Biſhops are an Order of Men of their own (not of Chriſt's) making. I was told that our Biſhops Order was founded in that of the 12 Apoſtles, and the Presbyters Order in the 70 Diſciples: Upon this I reſolved to ſee if the 12 and the 70 were different Orders, or no, and read over the 10th Chap. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> the 3d and 6th of <hi>Mark,</hi> and the 9th of <hi>Luke,</hi> in which places the Power which Chriſt gave to the 12 is ſet forth, which amounteth to this, <hi>viz.</hi> a Charge to Preach the Goſpel, a Power to work Miracles in caſting out Devils, healing the Sick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I alſo read in the 10th Chapter of <hi>Luke,</hi> that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58890:15"/>the 70 were ſent forth for the ſame Reaſon, and with the ſame expreſs Power as were the 12, <hi>viz.</hi> To preach the Goſpel, heal the Sick, and caſt out Devils, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.9.17. And he telleth the 70 at the 16th Verſe, <hi>That he who heareth them, heareth him; and he who deſpiſeth them, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him,</hi> as he had ſaid to the 12, in <hi>Matthew</hi> 10.40. Indeed they were only added to the number of the 12, <hi>Becauſe</hi> (as 'tis ſaid there) <hi>the Harvest was great, and the Labourers few,</hi> i. e. becauſe Multitudes followed Chriſt, and were diſpoſed to become Chriſtians, therefore he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed the number of his Apoſtles, or Teaching Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. I can find no Footſteps of any Juriſdiction given to the 12 over the 70, or indeed over any body elſe; and in the 18th Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> where Chriſt ſpeaketh of binding and looſing, 'tis manifeſt from the firſt Verſe, that his diſcourſe was made to his Diſciples. So in the 20th of <hi>John,</hi> the Holy-Ghoſt and Power of remitting and retaining Sins, was given to the Diſciples which met together after Chriſt's death, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19. in which meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there might be ſome of the 70 as well as ſome of the 12: 'Tis certain the 70 received the Holy-Ghoſt, and if Baptiſm be a Key of Admiſſion into the Church, they had it: If binding or looſing be declaring wherein we are bound in duty, and wherein we may uſe our liberty; if remitting and retaining Sins be declaring what Iniquity God will forgive, and what he will not; the 70 ſhared this Power with the 12. As for delivering up to Satan, and inflicting Diſeaſes; ſince 'twas a miraculous Power, which we read not that Chriſt appropriated to the 12, we have no reaſon to think 'twas detained from the 70. If then Chriſt appointed but one Order, <hi>viz.</hi> that of Teachers, the Order of Rulers dignified themſelves above, and diſtinguiſhed themſelves from their Brothren, yet I am willing to ſubmit to thoſe Powers, which the Laws of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58890:16"/>
               <hi>England</hi> have given to the Biſhops, though what they claim by Divine Right, I eſteem as an Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>Moreover (ſays he) although I am become a Chriſtian, I have not ceaſed to be an <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot be in party with the Biſhops, who by their falſe-prerogative Doctrines, and other ſhameful Aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo lately betray'd the Charters and Liberties, Rights and Privileges of their Country, were ſetting up an abſolute irreſiſtible Power in K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. which being demiſed to K. <hi>James,</hi> endangered not only the Liberty and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, but Body and Soul of the Nation. Nor can I ſo ſoon forget how their long debates, about admitting the <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>Orange,</hi> our Good and Great King, to the Sovereignty, was the occaſion of ſpilling ſo much Proteſtant Blood in <hi>Ireland;</hi> nor the late Proteſtation of ſome of the chief of their Party againſt his Majeſties Right to the Crown; nor how careful they have been ſince, that (as it now falls out) he ſhould have no pretence to any right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Title. If any Clergy-man was ſo honeſt as to Preach up his Right, as juſtly grounded on the Conſent of the People, (as Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi> for inſtance) he muſt lie under pain of the Church's higheſt diſpleaſure, though otherwiſe ever ſo Orthodox and Conformable; ſo that ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Title of Conqueſt is burnt by the Parliament, and the Matrimonial Title is (to the great grief of all good Men) dead and buried with the Queen; it remaineth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Holy Church, that he hath no Title at all, but only bare Poſſeſſion; and this they mean when they call him <hi>de facto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I cannot find that they will allow him to be King of the Clergy ſo much as <hi>de facto.</hi> Alas! his Livings, whereby alone he is capable to oblige them to call to mind their now forgotten Loyalty, which of late years they preached up, as the ſumm of the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58890:16"/>Alas! theſe good Things are taken out of his hands by the Conquering Biſhops, that the Clergy may have a ſeparate Intereſt from the State on this ſide the Water, and be led to pay an intire Allegiance to the holy Order. When <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. came to know that his Biſhops ſwore Allegiance to the <hi>Pope,</hi> he began to think of ſome ways and means how to make himſelf King of his Clergy, which he ſaw could not be done but by caſting out the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Power; and hence ſprung that King's Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Politicks, rather than Religion. And if our good King were ſenſible of the Reaſons why an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Papacy is ſettled in a Committee of Six, <hi>viz.</hi> to fix the Obedience of the Clergy on themſelves excluſively, (for no Man can ſerve two Maſters) I doubt not but he would think fit to demand what is ſo much wanted, <hi>viz.</hi> the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance of the Clergy to their King; if he diſſolves this Committee he may ask and have, for where their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, there their Hearts will be alſo. For theſe Reaſons (ſaid he) I ſhall be cautious how I enter into Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip, ſince I plainly ſee that every Party of Chriſtians embodied, organized, clergy'd and modelled into a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Church, caſteth an awe upon the Sovereign Power, and ſuffereth it not to provide equally for the Common Good of the Subject, but will appropriate the <hi>ſalus publica,</hi> and influence the Government to ſerve its own particular, its own private Ends.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I have given you an account of thoſe Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which have brought forth <hi>Deiſm.</hi> But yet theſe very Prejudices without a ſtrong aſſiſtance of Paſſion, could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have wrought upon Men to caſt off Revelation; for you ſee the ſame Prejudices remain in the <hi>Deist</hi> turn'd Chriſtian. Whoſoever therefore, upon the fore-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reaſons turneth <hi>Deist,</hi> cannot be excuſed, tho' I could heartily wiſh all theſe Pretences could be taken away from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58890:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>'em. I am far from begrudging the Biſhops and Clergy that ſmall Maintenance, which by Law is ſettled upon them; and, I hope, they have no other aim in diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Offices, but to ſave our Souls, by imprinting on our Hearts the Reaſon, the Excellency and Advantages of the Law of Chriſt. I hope alſo, that they comport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Common Intereſt of their Native Country, and of the Proteſtant Religion throughout the World. Truly I could wiſh that Notional Divinity were laid aſide for Practical, and that unintelligible Myſteries were not inſiſted on, as matters of neceſſary Belief. He, who lately wrote his Thoughts of the Cauſes and Occaſions of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, might have conſider'd, that he, who cloggeth the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God with Abſurdities, miſ-leadeth Men beyond <hi>Deiſm.</hi> I pray God give me his Grace, by which I may ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely conform my ſelf to the Law of Chriſt, and I will never concern my ſelf with the Speculative Drs. in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. And I heartily join with our Church in that Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Give grace, O heavenly Father, to all Biſhops and Curates, that they may both by their Life and Doctrine, ſet forth thy true and lively Word, and rightly and duly Adminiſter thy holy Sacraments.</hi> By this they would bring Souls to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, gain the Love of all good People, ſecure their own Temporal Intereſts, ſtop the Mouths of their Adverſaries, and compel the <hi>Deists</hi> to become Chriſtians.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am, Sir, Your Affectionate,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>If your Curioſity ſhould lead you to be an Ear witneſs of ſuch Diſcourſes I have here Written to you, when I come to Town, which will be as ſoon as the Parliament Sits, I will endeavour to give you that Satisfaction.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58890:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
